So this is from the Samutanica
because suppose a foolish incompetent
unskillful cook was to serve a king or
his minister with a faster way of
courage superbly sour and bitter pungent
and sweet hot and mild salty and bland.
But that cook didn't pick up the hint or
the sign of his own master. Today my
master preferred this sauce or he
reached for it or he took a lot of it or
he praised it. Today my master preferred
the sour or bitter or prominent or sweet
or hot or mild or salty sauce or he
preferred the bland sauce or he reached
for the bland one or he took a lot of it
or he praised it.
That foolish, incompetent, unskillful
cook doesn't get presented with clothes,
wages or bonuses. Why is that? Because
he doesn't pick up the hint of his own
master. In the same way, a foolish, incompetent,
In the same way, a foolish, incompetent,
unskillful piku abides maintaining
perspective of the body concurrently
with the body, diligent, aware, and
recollected, having subdued, longing,
and upset in regards to the world. As he
m sorry as he abides maintaining
perspective of the body concurrently
with the body his mind does not become
composed and the defilements are not
given up he doesn't pick up the hint of
that and then goes on for the other
satipana feelings
um mind and phenomena
and then the
suta continues
That foolish, incompetent and skillful
Biku doesn't gain pleasant abidings
right in the present experience, nor
does he gain recollection and awareness.
Why is that? Because that foolish,
incompetent, unskilled Biku does not
pick up the hint of his own mind.
Suppose an astute, competent, skillful
cook was to serve a ruler or their
minister with a vast array of curries,
superbly sour, bitter, pump and sweet,
hot and mild, salty and bland. And that
cook picked up the hint of his own
master. Today my master preferred this
sauce or he reached for it or he took a
lot of it or he praised it and so on.
Then it says that astute competent
skillful cook gets presented with close
wages and bonuses. Why is that? Because
he picks up the hint of his own master.
Now then it says in the same way a wise
competent skillful beu abides maintain
perspective of the body concurrently
with the body diligent aware and
recollected having subdued longing and
upsetting regard to the world. As he
abides maintaining perspective of the
body concurrently with the body his mind
becomes composed and the defilements are
given up. He picks up the hint of that
and then it goes on for the other um
satipatana in the same way.
So the first thing that stands out to me
is that this is talking about bikus
about the skillful and unskillful biku.
And secondly that both the skillful and
the unskillful piku
um
what does it say? They both must have
understood to some degree
because they are abiding you know body
concurrently with body feeling
concurrently with feeling and they have
already given up longing for the world
and so on. That is the case for both the
skillful and the unskillful beu. So
talking about the hint or the sign of
the mind. What is it that this
unskillful beu is overlooking or hasn't
understood that that that prevents him from gaining
that that that prevents him from gaining
the right composure and giving up the
developments as it says.
What would you say?
Well, the most um direct way of
explaining is that if you don't see the
sign of the mind, you don't see the
problems to begin with.
So, you don't see what you have to
abandon. Um so,
Um so,
the thing is as it says, you abandon
longing and upset in regard to the
world. But um I mean that's already an
achievement of course but uh and it
wouldn't have been accomplished without
the prerequisites of virtue and sense
restraint which are there because it's
saying that it's
um but
in regard to the world is one thing and
now you could say there's long version
in regard to your own mental states
and that part isn't going to be
uh as easily abandoned just because you
uh keep the precepts and even if like
you don't want anything in the world,
you don't depend on any external uh
pleasures, you don't seek sensuality,
you don't act out of aversion and all
these things, you can still have a um
perverted attitudes in a very subtle way
of course uh in regard to your own
mental states and that's where the
defilements are And that's why they
can't be abandoned accidentally because
uh it's only when you see the sign of
the mind that you would be able to do
well when you see the sign of the mind
which is where the filements are that
you would be able to do anything about
them anything if you if you suddenly
find yourself without defilements and
you don't know what you did it just
happened that's that's because you didn't
that's that's because you didn't
actually
see the side of the mind and then purify
it. You just got another experience that
doesn't that happens not to provoke your
defilements, a peaceful state of mind or whatever
a peaceful state of mind or whatever
that just happens circumstantially
happens not to provoke your mind.
But the um so let let's let's give a
concrete example. So as it's saying
there it's um yeah so one of the things
that stands out is that both of them are
actually doing the same thing. It's not
saying that one of them is doing one
practice and the other one like he
hasn't been given the right instruction
or something like that
or he he doesn't have the right
meditation object.
What it's saying is that
both of them are attempting to do the
same thing. They're attempting to be
mindful of the body feelings uh mind and
and dhas are phenomena. But that's not
in and of itself what makes it
wholesome. It's not that just because
you're reflecting on the body uh which
is already I mean seeing the body
concurrently with the body that's
already uh a step ahead of what most
people would be doing in their
meditation practice. They wouldn't even
be doing that. They would be focusing on
the body focusing on particular sense
objects like basically regarding the body as an
like basically regarding the body as an
object in front of you that you can
focus on.
Yeah. So that's uh growing out of that
is already a step forward and and from
where most people are and that would put
you in the position of this unskillful
big which is okay. So he's trying to see
the broader context of his experience as
you know as the body as feelings as as
mind and so on.
But but the growing out of it is by
means of yonika.
Yeah. So
that's how you grow out of this focusing
on things exclusively. Well, not even
through just by changing your views by
recognizing that you know the
defilements will never be on the level
of objects and
uh any effort that you might be putting
into that will necessarily be secondary
to the path because the path is on the
level of your mind's attitude towards
objects. So um just by recognizing that um you
So um just by recognizing that um you
know any amount of focusing you might do
there's perfectly
perfectly
like space there for defamments to be
there as you're focusing that already shows
as you're focusing that already shows
you that practice is is perfectly
um inadequate for what you're looking
for. Uh so just by growing out of that
and recognizing okay no I'm supposed to
be seeing the nature of my experiences
while those experiences are happening
within obviously the container of
virtuous sensory strain not just out
there in the world trying to be mindful
um
and then uh you recognize that but even
then that you you can still have these
background unrecognized attitudes there
and that's where the sign of the mind
is. So as I was going to say you can
have let's say you're you're
contemplating uh something you read from the sutras
uh something you read from the sutras
you're contemplating the impermanence of
the body you're contemplating
uh the nature of feelings you're
contemplating um anything basically that that's in its
um anything basically that that's in its
u in its content is wholesome it's like
a good object to put if you want to call
it that way
but the problem is wholesomeness as I
think we described in in one of the
previous talks is never defined by what
you're attending to by the content of
your experience. So
um the wholesomeness or the or the greed
version delusion or absence of it that
you would have there is defined by what
is your mind's attitude towards that
contemplation you're doing.
That's where you would find the side of
the mind. So it's the same object is
there. that you change something
different. But let's say the these um
But let's say the these um
peripheral kind of
meanings that are floating there
in relation to what you're attending to.
And what would be one of the most um
relevant examples for people? It would
be the sense of anticipation,
expectation and craving for special
experiences and insights to arise out of
the meditation.
You would be doing the same practice,
the same uh wholesome
contemplation and reflection that you
read from the sutas, but with that uh
taken for granted background of
anticipation and desire. And you
wouldn't see that actually your
contemplation should be applying to that
not just robotically continuing to focus
on the well it's not even focus anymore
it's a contemplation factually like it
says he's doing it properly
but because he fails to include that
into the picture as well
well the defilement won't be abandoned
because it will never be abandoned
accidentally it needs to be seen
in order to be abandoned so
you can do that practice for 100 appears
that the filament continues to float
there and it's never going to go away by
itself unless you uh unless you see it
unless you address it that way. So I was
saying that these background attitudes
that you just described that that is
basically synonymous with the
development. Yeah. Like you will never I mean the
Yeah. Like you will never I mean the
foundments um they will be let's say
um
confirmed or uh cemented by things in
the foreground that you can attend. So
obviously you have a sensual state of
mind and you are also um actively
proliferating sensual thoughts. Of
course that's unh wholesome as well but
because of the state of mind that's what
defines not the presence of those images
in your mind
but the attitude of the mind towards it
is what defines that
because I mean you can be thinking about
the same even even in your ordinary
experience to an ordinary person who
doesn't practice they can see on some
occasions I can be having exactly the
same perceptions in my mind
there isn't lust and on other occasions
the same thing is there and there is
lust If why is that? If the if the content of
If why is that? If the if the content of
the experience were all um that all that
all that is relevant to define whether a
comment is there, that wouldn't be the
case. Whenever you have these specific
objects, you would have lust and and
only then would you be able to justify
an object observation practice because
then it would mean okay, you just stick
to these objects and that means it's
going to be wholesome always.
But it's not like that. So somebody
let's say sits down to right they notice
there's a sensual thought present
but then now you're saying that the
actual hindrance of sensuality is not
just the presence of that thought in
fact it's it's actually whether there's
a background attitude to delight welcome
and proliferate that thought further or
not just even the thought just you could
say in regard to feelings in general. So
for example that monk there it's saying
it's uh abandon he has abandoned already
longing and diversion in regards to the
world. In other words he's not having
particular essential thoughts anymore
because that requires active volition
and uh he would have already abandoned
that. felt behind his efforts at that
time to purify his mind.
He doesn't see that there is still these
more subtle implications to that same
practice that he's doing
that he he needs to um
he needs to start including that as well
in his renunciation in order for the
mind to be actually purified.
It's not enough just to not be having
sensual thoughts or aversive thoughts.
And that's usually where uh people would
then sort of like um jump the gun so to
say where they see okay so I stopped
having these uh coarse
objects and now it's time to start
concentrating on an object and that's
where you try to take a shortcut
what you actually had to do I mean
according to the sut
is uh start recognizing yes I am not
peaceful like the comments are clearly
still there. I'm still liable to breed a
diversion delusion even though I have
stopped acting out of them like I have I
am perfectly restrained
and what you need to do there now is start
what you need to do there now is start
to see the signs of the mind not go and
start concentrating which will basically
it's exactly the opposite direction of
seeing the sign of the mind. It's like
actively ignoring the sign of the mind
and um
If you if you start uh that the problem
with that is that will never be
something that um you achieve overnight.
Those signs of the mind um it will never
be like a sudden epiphany that comes up
for you one day. It will be it is
necessarily a gradual development.
Yeah. Um so it's it's starting to notice your
Um so it's it's starting to notice your
own intentions.
That's that's basically what it comes
down to. It's intentions not in the
sense of um decisions which is what
people usually like you could say you
could present the concept that we're
talking about you could present it that
way the average person who doesn't see
the sign of the mind what they think in
terms with in terms of intentions what
they think of is decisions
like I decide on a very course level I
decide to do this as like super uh uh
coarse and and deliberate
With the signs of the mind, there's
still intentions like the these
impurities, these defilements that you
would get to see when you see the sign
of the mind. They're still intentional.
It's not that it's happening by itself,
but um it is on a much more subtle level
than what you're generally used to. And
the discernment of that basically like
pulling you pulling you back in the
beginning. All you see is these very
coarse uh actions and that's why you
have to start with the precepts like in
the beginning
the only thing a person can be sure
about is that breaking the precepts is
unh wholesome.
Mhm. Uh and if you that's why it's a brighter
Uh and if you that's why it's a brighter
training. You work through that and then
these more subtle layers of the same
principle start to be revealed up to the
point where you can see your own
attitude in regard to your own thoughts.
Not the thoughts themselves but your
attitude in regard to those thoughts. In
the same way like
it's not that the
you know it's not that the presence of
uh an attractive person in front of you
is sensual desire.
No, it's you
it's you
uh engaging with a person
intentionally for sensual reasons that is sensual
for sensual reasons that is sensual
desire. And that same principle you you
eventually bring it inwards towards your
own thoughts. It's not the presence of
these things that is unh wholesome. It's
your attitude in regard to them.
And again, it's not something you'll be
able to figure out figure out overnight.
It's it's a by maintaining that that
container of uh virtue and sensory
strain. It's like a like a like a fence
that you put around your mind and then
the suffering that's left there that
forces you to deal with it like not you
again not not in the sense of find the
answer suddenly but it's like it's
leaving you no choice again if you
refrain from trying to take a shortcut
and and going into the route of
absorption and distraction
uh it will force you to start
recognizing as it says there. What is it
that I'm feeding? What why is it that
the king is still not pleased?
Yeah. So, let's go into that. But but
one step back still because we we
mentioned that to see sign of the mind
which are these attitudes towards not
only things in the world but now also
your own thoughts. You mentioned offense
which is the virtue and the sense
strain. But we should also emphasize
that without solution this sign in your
mind is not going to become apparent. So
perhaps we should get out first before
we go and discuss the simil.
Yes. So actually there's there's another
suta that's quite relevant that says um
I think it's 668
and it says without so it gives a a bit
of a series um and it says without uh
learning to a monk who delights in
seclusion he won't be able to um
not with delights in company you mean?
Yeah, sorry. A monk who lies in company,
he won't be able to delight the
seclusion. A monk who's not able to
delight the seclusion, he won't be able
to see the signs of the mind. A monk who
cannot see the signs of the mind, he
won't be able to get the right view.
A monk who who doesn't fulfill the right
view, he won't be able to fulfill right.
And one who doesn't fulfill right sadi
cannot abandon the one who doesn't
abandon the cannot achieve nibbana. So
um
why is it then that seclusion is
necessary for seeing the side of the
mind? Well, that's another fence. That's
like the the most um
when you're in seclusion. So when you're
seclusion having established virtue and
restraint beforehand because as it says
it's not just being seclusion it's
actually preferring seclusion and it's
inconceivable that you'll be able to be at ease in
that you'll be able to be at ease in
seclusion and generally prefer it if you
haven't established these prerequisites
because even in the sutas it's shown
like monks who hadn't developed
themselves enough they would go into
seclusion and the first thing that would start
and the first thing that would start
arising essential thoughts aversive
thoughts and and
um all sorts of fun wholesome states.
So um the thing is like again because
the whole shortcut of meditation
techniques comes in people are able
actually don't realize what the baseline
of their mind would be
when they go into seclusion if they
don't start distracting themselves in
that direction.
And and that's actually how you would be
able to know if you have developed these
prerequisites enough. Like when you go
into seclusion and you don't do like you
don't do anything but you also don't
actively try not to do anything if that
makes sense. Like you're not trying to
suppress your thoughts. You're not just
you just within that seclusion. You get
up, you walk back and forth.
You don't distract yourself with you
know reading or or or breaking
essentially breaking the precepts. And
there you start to see um whether
there's a certain stability to the mind
naturally um in that in that open environment like
um in that in that open environment like
half open half closed let's say or uh
whether you know it starts going all
over the place and that tells you that
you won't be like your prerequisites are
still insufficient for you to be able to
delight in true solusion
generally not distracting yourself even
with your meditation and and and all
these things because something that
distracts you cannot be medit cannot be
rightly called meditation.
No. So this is already like so first of all
So this is already like so first of all
seclusion has to be understood like no
no presence of other people.
Yeah. That's what seclusion is. So we cannot
That's what seclusion is. So we cannot
equate that with the average labor tree.
Seclusion means on your own you know
somewhere door closed.
Yeah. As as soon as other people are
present, certain attitudes again on that same
certain attitudes again on that same
background level, they almost inevitably
are going to be there and you and you
you will not have the capacity to see
those attitudes and and question them
because they're so deeply ingrained
that it's it's almost almost as if
they're automatic. They're not
ultimately. Uh so an arroant wouldn't
have those attitudes after you know
having finished the path but
for you starting from the beginning
it's like you know um someone like
lifting a heavy weight for somebody
who's not strong enough there's no way
that they won't be doing it with bad
form even though technically it's not
even though technically it's not
absolutely necessary. You could lift the
weight with good form in this case
practically speaking it's not possible.
So you need to actually withdraw
yourself first and uh like when you're
in seclusion that will allow you to um
have more space to to actually start
questioning these attitudes in your mind
including the attitudes or whatever
meditation instruction you have
received. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah.
Because now the question is why are you
even going to do something formal when
you have already been keeping precepts
practicing senses train and are
observing the body is occlusion.
Yeah. So because that's how it's going
to be probably for most people.
Yeah. That would already betray a view
that you know you think you you you
just really want to shortcut. You don't
want to discern the sides of your mind
cuz if you if you really did you would
be questioning wait why do I want to do
this in the first place? Because that in
itself could be a defilement.
Yeah. And then like if you ran with it
with that intention from the start,
nothing that comes up again as I said
100 years after doing that practice will
undo the fact that you took a wrong turn
from the start.
Yeah. So um
So um
uh the the all the insights that you
would get from
absorption practices quote unquote
they're on the level of sense objects.
That's precisely like you know what what
you would read is all these experiences
of a you know um a flash of of
consciousness arising and ceasing and all these things
arising and ceasing and all these things
and all of that is just sense objects
and the sign of the mind is not a sense
object. It's not it's not a it's not
even a specific thought that you catch
or something.
It's um as I said a discernment of the
attitude in regard to your thoughts.
Yeah. So basically it means seeing your mind
So basically it means seeing your mind
which is always necessarily a peripheral
phenomenon seeing that as a phenomenon whereas
seeing that as a phenomenon whereas
before obviously it's there but you
don't see it. Mhm.
Um so
that's that's why it's it's called a
sign or a nimar actually I translated it
as hint
so it doesn't give the impression
because nimita is is already has all
these associations of you know you're
meditating and this nima comes up
but it's not that it's
if it would be while you're expecting
for this thing to come up
seeing that attitude in yourself and
then it's not that obviously it's not
that um catching it, you know, magically
solve the issue.
Catching the signs of the mind allows
you to do the work.
Mhm. It's not that that that's that's it.
It's not that that that's that's it.
Yeah. So now
let's make a move from here. So suppose
so there's two things we can do. We can
either unpack the semon and see which
ingredients are there in in order to
make sure that that we understand this
simile properly and then we can clear up
what is the actual work to be done once
the sign of the mind has been highly
discerned. Yeah. So the the simile is is actually
Yeah. So the the simile is is actually
you know whenever you see something in
the sutas like that you you don't just
kind of um impose your notions on it but
actually you step back and see if the
Buddha chose that similarly it must be
for a reason. Mhm.
Um so in this case what is the
similarity between this principle we've
been describing of the side of the mind
is an indirect thing that cannot be
directly observed as a sense object
and the uh preferences of a king that
the cook would be would be noticing.
Mhm. It's basically the fact that um he
It's basically the fact that um he
doesn't tell you I want this or I want
that. He doesn't doesn't make a gesture
with with his hands or something. Um
it's indirect as it says. He took a lot
of this one. He spoke in praise of that
one. But it's it's if you're just um if
the cook, let's say, is just totally
focused on his self-centered point of
view in what not not even deliberately
just by failing to to
actually um discern those signs. He will
be thinking, "Oh, this food is is
everyone likes it, so I'm just going to
go with this because
who doesn't like chocolate cake or
something?" And he ignores the fact that
And he ignores the fact that
the ripeness of the dish depends on the
cook, not on what you think would be
right. No, it depends on the king.
No, it depends on the king.
H sorry, depends on the king.
Yes. Not on what the cook thinks you
would be right. So in the same way like
you read something from the sutas you
assume that that in itself
just doing that is going to make it
right yes
yes
whereas if that's not what the cook need
what the king wants it's not right even
if it's the best dish in the world that
everybody else would like
for him it's not
yeah so what does king stand for in the
well the mind good so um the the but
again that's the
clarification that needs to be made
because sometimes people read that
similly and think oh so the king I just
have to find what gives rise to the most
pleasure or something like that so
uh um because it is that yeah please
pleasing the king and so on
but it's see if you start out from this
from the beginning with the expectation
of pleasure that's already you not
seeing the signs of your mind you don't
see that see you you embark on this
quest of giving the mind what it wants
because you're suffering.
And so you would be failing to question
the fact that the reason why you're
suffering is because there's craving
right then and there as a sign that
you're not discerning.
Uh and that if you were to just address
that, you would actually fix the problem
without having to fabricate or give rise
to anything secondary. Mhm.
Uh so it's it's uh what you're feeding
the mind. It's not again like oh today I
have to do breath meditation because uh
you know
I feel like it's
Yeah. Yeah. Or or that that's what
that's what's going to uh please the
mind most. It's no it's any of these
things any of these
uh meditations or contemplations if you
do them correctly
that's not in itself like the the
meditation itself is not what's right or
wrong as I just said it's
what is the let's say counter attitude
that's associated with that. So if you
are what you're feeding the king, let's
say is
you're either going with it, let's say
there's a there's a essential tendency
or or craving for pleasure, your
intentions that the intentions that you
exert will either be going with the
grain or against the grain of that tendency.
or against the grain of that tendency.
And if you don't know 100% that they're
going against the grain, they're going
with the grain.
That's how it works. So, um, what you're
feeding the mind, quote unquote, really,
is the intention behind your
contemplation, not the contemplation
itself. And that's why in the sutas, you
have all these different uh uh
approaches that you can take. And none
of them is more special than the other
in and of themselves because what will
make them work quote unquote is uh the
attitude with which you pack it together
let's say. Um so there's always going to
be two components obviously you know if
you're just reflecting on I don't know
some random
uh
Hindu mantra or something
even if you have the right attitude well
I mean that's not really
but so to some extent yes it has to be
something from the sutas
but there's two components to it there's
your attitude behind it
and the contemplation itself.
Yeah. So, um, that's where that that
that is really what you're feeding the
king. That's that's what and you feed
the king what he needs only if you can
see where where is it that he's
inclining. If you can see those states at uh at the
If you can see those states at uh at the
back of your mind, quote unquote, then
you know what is it that needs to be
actually addressed with the same
contemplation. Mhm.
Not that like I need to do another one
now because the mind is like this.
Mhm. So it's not like you know sometimes
So it's not like you know sometimes
people think oh if I have sensual desire
I need to do a suba if I have a version
I need to do meta. If I have this I need
to counter it with this. And that's not
that's not you could do the same
contemplation for everything
because it would all depend on seeing
where the craving is and using that
contemplation as a means to
let's say reestablish the right the
right perspective that stars or or
season to provide fuel for that craving
which you need to see before. So then
practically speaking those
contemplations that for people allow
them to see that background attitude
most clearly that will be for them the
best way to go about it right so the
less abstract or intellectual the
contemplation is because that's all in
the other way. So you you want to pick
up a theme or contemplation that that
has the highest chance that it's not
going to be disconnected from that
background attitude. In fact, the whole
contemplation should go in that
direction. That's the whole point.
Yeah. So, so in that sense again it
wouldn't be what would make it right or
wrong would be that through that
contemplation you would be able to
bundle it together with the right
attitude. Yeah.
Yeah.
So um uh in that sense yeah for
different people there will be different
things that will be more uh suitable
like the sutas would say for those who
have a strong tendency towards the
vomits um you know these contemplations
of death and and the suba and all these
things. um they would be more
beneficial, but not again not because
if you do them if you do them in and of
themselves, you can perfectly still uh
bundle them up with the wrong thing.
Yeah. With you know, you can be doing a suba
With you know, you can be doing a suba
why
fundamentally you can still be doing
with an attitude of craving
against these thoughts that are arising
by themselves. You're not willing to
endure them. You're not willing to see
that they arise on their own and that
your attitude your your your
responsibility is a delight in those
thoughts. You just want to get rid of
them and you keep doing that blindly
with that background attitude. Even
though technically the object of the
suba is wholesome
for you at that time it's not.
You're not seeing that actually the king
is is um that what the king needs is not
to get rid of these things. It's uh that
attitude of delight that needs to be
abandoned. Yeah. Or Yeah. I see. And so um that's
Yeah. Or Yeah. I see. And so um that's
what's that's what would make any
contemplation right. So in that sense
you would be you could be doing the same
thing again
you're do you're doing the contemplation
it's not working you recognize that as
it says the mind is not becoming
composed the voms are not being
abandoned the pressure is increasing not
decreasing you're you're getting even
more agitated than before you don't
change it up
that's that's like I mean you can but it
it will still not work on the level that
it
Unless you start seeing the attitude
behind that's making it not work. It's
not the contemplation.
It's your kind of um unquestioned
attitudes that are there. So
kind of the the the the suffering that
comes up and that's why again going back
to seclusion and so on when you're in
seclusion and your mind is kind of uh
going everywhere.
So that that's another thing actually we
should clarify before we go on. When
you're in seclusion, the whole point is
to allow your mind to move to some
extent. You don't want to be, you know, bottling
You don't want to be, you know, bottling
it up into into uh this or that uh kind
of overly uh controlled
uh mental environment. It's you
basically within the precepts within
that environment you allow your mind to
move and then uh even thinking about
random things as long as it's not
obviously unh wholesome and there you're
going to be able to see that's going to
reveal the suffering
and u the suffering is not in your mind
thinking about those things. It's in the
attitude while those thoughts are
present. And that's where that's where
then you will be forced to start
addressing that seclusion kind of brings
out those symptoms. That's it. And then
that forces you to look where is that
illness? Where is it? And you don't you
don't uh you don't give up on this until
you actually find it. And you will know
with certainty that uh that was the only
way to actually deal with it. You could
have distracted yourself. uh with
something that would have temporarily
suppressed the symptoms but that would
have been basically just useless in the
end it doesn't help.
Yeah. So, so now okay suppose somebody
is in solution right meeting all these
prerequisites that we have discussed so
far and then a sensual thought comes up
say somebody notices is not concerned
with no focusing exclusively on that
thought but they begin to see this
background attitude of either leaning
towards and delighting in that thought
or saying I shouldn't have any sense of
thought I want to get rid of it as soon
as possible because that's my duty as a
monkm M
and they begin to see some glimpse of
that attitude towards those thoughts
while they are present
then what's next? Well, that's it.
That's it. So that attitude of what next
like so you already saw that those
thoughts are unh wholesome. You're
already not giving into them.
You recollect okay well this body is
impermanent. any um inclination that I
may have to indulge in the objects that
belong to this body will make me even
more liable to suffer when that body
breaks apart.
Yes. And that's it. So
And that's it. So
yeah,
for as long as the mind doesn't again
start delighting in essential thoughts,
your duty is done for that moment. If
you start, you know,
trying to do
keep going, then
you don't see you're you're not seeing a
sign. Yeah. So then well then you're
Yeah. So then well then you're
overlooking some other background
attitude. Yeah. Exactly. So you're not seeing now
Yeah. Exactly. So you're not seeing now
the attitude of expectation. You're just
running towards this experience you
think you should have.
Yeah. And that's actually the suffering.
And that's actually the suffering.
Yeah.
Whether the experience comes later on or
whatever you you still didn't understand why
you you still didn't understand why
initially you were suffering to begin
with. So it's not really solving the the
So it's not really solving the the
liability to suffering.
Um so that's it. So you you notice the
sign of the mind you notice the
inclination of the mind and that's why
then said the sus would then say your
job is then not to get rid of it asana
itself says actually he knows lustful
mind is lustful mind he knows averse
mind is averse mind he knows distracted
mind is distracted mind that's it
and yeah that's defined as purity actually
yeah that's defined as purity actually
yeah yeah so you um
you basically basically for as long as
you don't lose sight of that and you
will lose sight of that when you either
fall uh again back into the sense
objects or you fall too much into the
side of um denying them and and trying
to replace them with uh other thoughts
that that you think are better.
You need to stay in the middle which is
you're not delighting in the thoughts
but you're also not trying to replace
them with others
and uh to that extent you're seeing the
side of the mind. So that's why it's
it's inextricably tied the middle way.
Um so it's not getting rid of the mind,
it's uh knowing it for what it is and
then not adding fuel to the unh
wholesome states that are there.
Yeah. And then when the when the mind is in
And then when the when the mind is in
the it obviously works the opposite way
as well. When the mind is in a wholesome
state, let's say when the five have been
abandoned, you also know that for
yourself and you know exactly how it
came about. Didn't happen by accident.
is because the whole time you were aware
of the king's preferences and you were
doing the right thing
and now the the king is in a in a in the
king is pleased and you know exactly how
to maintain that and there is nobody in
the world that can suddenly make you
lose that which you worked for.
So like when people say oh I I lost my
samadei or something that that's that's
because they didn't have it to begin
with. If you see the signs in the mind,
there is no way except your own
intention. Well, if it is right and to begin with,
Well, if it is right and to begin with,
which happens on the basis of seeing the
sign of the mind, there is nothing
except your own intention which can
um you know make a decrease.
So um
the the
you could basically say as a kind of
illustration slightly coarse but it
might be useful. It's sign of the mind
would be
wherever you're looking at even mentally
whatever you're directing your beam of
attention if you want to put it that way
the side of the mind is what's around
around that. So the same way I'm looking
here now and the back of my head
like I know that there's stuff back
there but I can't directly look at it.
but I can't directly look at it.
Mhm.
And while I'm looking at outside I know
that there's stuff back there and I
might know let's say that you know
there's something behind my head and if
I lean too far back I'm going to hit my
head but I'm not directly looking at it.
No. So that's that could be one
practical way of of because if you try
to turn towards it well now see the back
of my head remains the back of my head
it will never change.
So is this the recollection and
awareness aspect?
Yeah. So actually that's another thing
that says it without seeing the side of
the mind you don't have recollection
awareness even though you might be you
know because usually mindfulness is is
thought of as uh consistent focusing or
observation of one thing
and u what this is saying is you might
do that as much as you want you don't
see the center of the mind you don't
have recollection and awareness no
because it's not awareness of like a I
mean it's even like a like a
doesn't even make sense to call
observation of one object awareness.
Because when the sutas say what is
awareness it says a monk is aware of his
thoughts as they arise as they endure as
they cease his feelings as they arise as
they endure as they cease. So can you
actually see those things as objects?
Mhm. The whole point is no, you can't
because those are those things are um
in order to like you can you can see
this the the thoughts themselves are
objects of course but your knowledge of
those things is not on the level of
objects. cannot be. So that's a general
principle of knowledge in general like
um you know how how does a um car
mechanic I think I might have given that
example before like he he knows um all
the the the
inner workings of the car and so on
that's not that knowledge is not a sense
object because if it were you you just show
because if it were you you just show
that to somebody else and he would have
exactly the same knowledge the car
mechanic does but it doesn't work like
So um it's uh it's it's the same with
with the knowledge of feelings,
knowledge of thoughts, knowledge of
these things. So if you're just watching
your thoughts, that becomes another
sense object. It's not knowledge
anymore. So uh yeah, that's one one practical way
So uh yeah, that's one one practical way
of thinking about it. It's always behind
your attention. That's the principle of
the mind. It but it is a phenomenon. So,
it's important not to mystify it and
thinking think that it's like it's it's
sort of it's not a phenomenon or it's or
it's hidden in my experience or
something like that. No, it's there.
It's it's just that in the same way.
It's not that the back of my head
doesn't exist or like what's behind me
doesn't exist.
It is there. It's just that if I focus
too much on what's in front of me, I
forget. You cannot sustain that knowledge of the
You cannot sustain that knowledge of the
backgrounds. So to the extent that you
lose yourself in others in front you
will be compromising that background
knowledge basically.
Yeah. And and obviously in front can be
uh on the most basic level science,
sights, sounds, smells, taste, touches,
but you can even in front would even
count as you know your ideas about the
dharma and your notions and and your
effort towards it and and your striving
that that becomes in front. Yeah. And in
behind that there's a whole range of
attitudes and and cravings and
expectations that if you're not actively
making an effort to to recognize they
will be driving that whole endeavor
and means for as much dharma in its
content might be present there. It's not
actually dharma.
Yeah. Because there's a relationship
between mind and it means intention.
Yeah. Exactly. So yeah, they're actually
derived from the same root. So uh mind
really is it's uh that's why again it's
also not not just something you catch as
some sort of a independent object that
you would catch a vision of something.
It's catching yourself doing things
catching yourself having attitudes that
you were taking for granted before. So
it's um you you you kind of it's not a
the best simile because uh it's kind of
in instantaneous whereas I've been
saying the side of the mind is something
that's developed gradually. You would
never have a sudden insight
where your recognition goes from 10% to
90 in one night. That's impossible. But
it serves to illustrate with uh like you
know you you see your nails
and for some reason like you seem to
have cuts
in your fingers and stuff and uh you
know they're kind of very
um you see that even though you're not
cutting your nails for some reason
they're always very short
and uh at some point you figure out that
you catch yourself biting your nails
and that's why actually your nails were
were in that condition. So it's the same
you um you have you find yourself
experiencing the suffering as a symptom
and what's causing that it's these
intentions that you don't see.
So that's that's where the sign of the
mind is and uh it would be slowly you
get to see through the evolution of the
gradual training see that sign of the
mind is has to be present throughout
even from the from the very start with
virtue but the extent of it is getting refined.
but the extent of it is getting refined.
So even just to keep the five precepts
like uh to keep them in their spirit, you can
uh to keep them in their spirit, you can
keep the the rules, you know, the letter
of the rules mechanically, but to be
able to keep keep the rules in their
spirit, you would already have to have a
basic recognition of the side of the
mind because uh you know uh let's say
lying like if you if you don't discern your
like if you if you don't discern your
intentions, if you don't see why is it
that you're saying what you're saying,
saying to another person. There might be
cases where you're not necessarily uh
telling an outright lie, but you're
intentionally misrepresenting the truth
because it's just too unpleasant to to
say it.
So, uh or you know, you you might be
keeping even let's say the eight
precepts and uh the precept on
entertainment, let's say. M you know you
might uh
in various occasions come across uh
news uh whatever videos newspapers and
stuff or or you might be using the internet
or or you might be using the internet
for some practical purpose
but unless you're able to see that
intention behind so why is it that I'm
actually choosing to do this right now
you you would be unable to really know
whether you're you're actually refrain
from entertainment or not because
anything can become entertainment just
like anything can be um uh a way of
distracting yourself. So then sense
restraint you won't be able to see what
what the sut define as grasping the
signs and features
uh of sense objects. You wouldn't be
able to see that nor would you be able
to see that longing and aversion that
would arise on account of that grasping
of science and features as the sisters
would say. Then the watchfulness of
envigilance purifying your mind from obstructive
purifying your mind from obstructive
states that would already be fully
contingent on seeing the sign of the
mind because otherwise you don't know
what obstructive states are.
Um and uh all the way up to the five
hindrances. So it's just refining the
same principle
of seeing the sign of the mind and uh
and it's important to see as well that
everyone has that uh ability to some
extent. So that's why for example uh in
some cases in the sutas these lay people
who got enlightened seemingly
instantaneously uh it's not because of some magical uh
uh it's not because of some magical uh
event or luck that they had it's because
well for whatever reason it might be in
their past lives or or even in their
present life their sensuality was not as
proliferated like they were not as um
constricted in that foreground level of
attention. that they they were able to see to some
that they they were able to see to some
extent that that peripheral domain um
the back of your head as I as I was
saying and um when the Buddha explains
these things they're actually able to
see them concretely in their own
experience here and now.
Yes. Uh so if the dharma doesn't if
hearing about these things the four
truths craving suffering sessation of
craving and all these things and you
don't have the right view that can only
be because the sign of the mind where
those recognitions that would allow
those recognition to land
is not there even if you made perfect
sense of all the information
not sufficiently
the concrete basis where you would see
where that craving is as I said always
behind you
that's not there. So even though yes you
agree with the fact that craving is
suffering uh because you read about it in the
uh because you read about it in the
sutas you won't it won't lead to the
inside of the right view
but uh everyone has that recognition of
the side of the mind on a basic level to
some degree because otherwise you
wouldn't be able to even start the
practice. So it's just that not it's not
enough to um to constitute the right abuse. You
to um to constitute the right abuse. You
you could you could say like you know
some people can't even catch themselves
uh telling lies
like it's just even even in in um even
if you tell them or or whatever they
just unable to
to recognize their own actions or not
not specifically things against the
precepts just anything
they they just have they operate almost
like like animals let's say without
recollection and without uh any
simultaneous awareness of the things
they're doing while they're doing them.
Uh-huh. Uh so um that already shows you and and
Uh so um that already shows you and and
some other people like you know they
they very sharp faculties like even even
though they haven't heard the dharma
um and uh they have a natural sense of
uh self-awareness to put it that way
not not in the new age sense of like
watching your knees and stuff because
nobody does that unless somebody has
told them.
uh whereas this is something that you
would be almost like ingrained into
whether you heard dumb or not this this
uh side of the mind. So um that shows
you that it's it's just a matter of u
cultivating it further. It's not
something that you have to like uh gain
uh for the first time or something like
that. It's just furthering
understanding the principle.
Yeah. Refining it.
Yeah. Yeah.
So a good way to illustrate how seeing
the signs of the mind would actually be
necessary even to purify your physical
and verbal actions would be let's say
you have an intention to do something
that's uh externally good or in a
Buddhist sense good like visiting a
monastery having dharma discussions uh
reading sutas and then you might assume
that that external property of that
action is what determines it is
wholesome failing to see that actually
it's the internal motivation behind it
that determines it as such. So and that
which can change from day to day. So if
one day you're doing that action because
um you crave for company, you were
bored, you want to have a good time, in
other words it's root rooted in passion,
then that same action is actually unh
wholesome even though other Buddhists
might be praising you in account of it
and whatnot. And it's exactly the same
principle on the mental level which is
what the suta is describing. So the
unskillful Biku assumes that just
thinking about the force it putan is
just contemplating these things and
going through the motions uh is good
failing to see that if it's driven by
passion aversion and delusion if that's
the driving force for those
contemplations that whole situation
becomes unh wholesome
and uh you would get to see the signs of
your mind in relation to actions on
those on any of those three domains
uh not through quickness of awareness
and uh developing sharp concentration
and being able to catch the sequence of
mind moments
uh but through self honesty even on the
mental level. So that's why if a person
doesn't have that basic self honesty
they can practice the dharma for decades
they won't get the right view because
they won't be seeing the signs of their
mind and uh seeing the signs of their
mind would result in abandoning the
first three fedters uh as uh angutaya
668 says because uh for example the
assumption of uh virtue and and uh
practices not just rights and rituals as
it's sometimes translated is precisely
rooted in um failing to see that even
these things that the Buddha factually
talked about the virtue and and um the
beneficial external practices are not wholesome in
external practices are not wholesome in
and of themselves. If they're done with
a with a internal motivation of passion,
aversion, and delusion, uh then they're
not wholesome. Obviously, that doesn't
mean that one shouldn't be virtuous
because it's more unh wholesome not to
be virtuous than to be virtuous with a
wrong attitude. Uh but it just means
that that's not enough in and of itself.
It's not enough to just go through those
motions and uh assume that that
automatically means uh the mind is being
purified.
to clarify sufficiently what this time
in mind.
Yeah. So one more thing you might might
mention. So uh how would you practically
go about it like uh you the first thing
you need to restrain is this tendency to
as I said be expecting a result.
That's that's kind of the most uh
it's actually the the simul gave. It's
it's the the handle.
You're not asking yourself
when is the axe handle going to wear
out. You're just using it.
You're just using it.
You're just using this axe
and you know that at some point it will
have to wear out.
It will not be tomorrow. It will not be
the day after tomorrow. It might not
even be next year. It might not even be
in two years. But you know for sure that
if you're using that axe as opposed to
leaving it there
the day where it's going to wear where
you will recognize that the axe handle
is worn out is coming closer.
Yeah. That's all you know.
That's all you know.
Yeah. But but exactly but there's no
doubt there. So somebody knows that what
they're doing is right. They're not
second guessing whether they're actually
wearing off this ax handle. They know
they are.
So the point being if you're making this
effort uh you will you are developing the
uh you will you are developing the
recognition on the side of the mind
because again it's not something you
have to wait for. No
it's just refining some principle that's
already there in your experience. So
there's nothing to wait for like
Yeah. So mind is not coming and going.
Yes. There. Yeah. So so it's like you
know uh getting better at um
yeah just exercising or something.
You're not you're not expecting some
magical day where like you already can
uh lift 10 pounds
then in one week you will be able to
lift 15
and then 20. So you like none of those
milestones are more special than than
the previous one. It's just the same
thing developing further. Yeah.
developing further. Yeah.
So, um
uh that that's the basically the way and
you don't know how many pounds you you
you will be able to lift. You need to be
able to lift
to get the right view. You just know you
will be factually be able to see like in
in hindsight that some progress has been
h has happened even before the right
view. you'll be able to see now I'm able
more able to see these these subtle
inclinations in mind that before I would
have been totally unaware of
and you know that it's that same
principle that if you take further you
know for sure eventually at that point
um
it will be enough for you to see the
form noble truths.
So um that's confirmation that that that
uh you'll be that you're going in the
right direction basically.
So because that's one of the obstacles
this this um sort of attitude of of
wanting to achieve something
not I mean it motivates you to to
practice of course but if you don't uh
see that as a phenomenon you just take
it for granted and run with it and think
that the practice the results just
happen to you regardless of um what your
attitudes towards those those that
endeavor is
then it's never going to because you're
not doing work that that would actually
make them come about.
Yeah.